That was a lot of talking for just switching between two different pages
Bu sadece iki farkl sayfa arasnda gei yapmak iin ok konuuyordu.
but this is important of course to know how to work with the router.
Ancak ynlendirici ile nasl alacam bilmek elbette nem tayordu.
Now however I want to make sure that we can also click on a single post and still load that because right
Ancak imdi, tek bir yayna tklayp hala ykleyebildiinden emin olmak istiyorum, nk u
now, nothing is happening when we're doing that.
anda bunu yaparken hibir ey olmuyor.
We also don't get an error,
Ayrca bir hata da edemiyoruz.
but nothing is happening.
Ama hibir ey olmuyor.
The reason for this is of course is that in our posts component where we have this handler for handling
ki mesajlarmzda burada postaya bir tklama ile ilgilenen bir ileyici olduumuz
a click on the post here, the postSelectedHandler is setting some state which is irrelevant because
post seili ileyici devletle ilgilenmiyorum nk alakasz baz durum gnderiyor.
I'm not handling the state anymore,
Bunun nedeni elbette
I don't even set up a default here.
Burada bir varsaylan ayarlamadm bile.
Now when clicking on this I actually now want to load the full post. For this
imdi buna tkladmzda bunun iin tam olarak yaz yklemek istiyorum.
we of course also need to determine where this full post should be shown.
Elbette, tam postun nerede gsterileceini de belirlememiz gerekir.
We could render it in the blog component instead of our post here,
Buradaki grevimiz yerine blok bileende oluturabiliriz.
we could load the full post in this place,
Bu yazya tam yaz ykleyebiliriz.
this is one option. Here however,
Ancak burada bir seenek var.
or no matter where we use actually, we need to be able to get dynamic routing parameter because if we
parametresini elde edebilmemiz gerekir, nk yaynlar ktsna bakarsak, her yaynn kimlii vardr.
have a look at our posts output, each post has ID
Veya nerede kullanyor olursanz olun, dinamik ynlendirme
And this ID of course is important because when we click on a post, we need to know which post that
Ve tabii ki bu fikir nemlidir, nk bir postaya tkladmzda
was, which post we want to load and that doesn't change when we use different routes.
hangi postay yklemek istediimizi ve farkl rotalar kullandmzda deimeyeceini bilmeliyiz.
Thankfully we have a way of getting the ID
Neyse ki kimlii elde etmenin bir yolu var.
so now we need to pass that ID as part of the URL so that in the post component, the full post component,
Dolaysyla, imdi bu kimlii, post bileenin tam post bileeninde yklediimizde, bu parametreyi alp
when we load it, we can get this parameter and load the appropriate post. For this,
bunun iin uygun postay ykleyebilmemiz iin bir paras olarak gndermeliyiz.
when defining the route, we need to inform react router about the fact that we now have a dynamic
Yn bulma konusunda bilgilendirmemiz gerektiinde ynlendiriciyi tekrar ynlendirip u anda bu URL'de dinamik
element in this URL.
bir eye sahip olduumuzu.
Obviously we will have posts with ID 1, 2 3 and we won't hardcode it like this,
Akas Kimliimiz 1 ile 3 arasnda olan yaynlara sahip olacaz ve byle sert kodlanmayacaz.
that would be a nightmare
Bu bir kabustur.
and in 99.
Ve 99'da.
9 percent of the applications, you don't even know how many possible values you have here.
Uygulamalarn yzde 9'unu burada ka muhtemel deeriniz olduunu bile bilmiyorsunuz.
So instead of hardcoding the different IDs, we define a flexible, a variable route parameter with colon
Bu nedenle, farkl kimlikleri sabit kodlama yerine, kolon ile esnek bir deiken rota parametresi tanmlyoruz ve daha
and then any name of your choice like ID or postID, I'll just use ID because it's shorter.
sonra kimliiniz veya ana makine kimliiniz Alceste kullandnz kimliiniz daha ksa olduundan setiiniz herhangi bir ad.
This will be replaced dynamically
Bu, dinamik olarak deitirilecek.
or essentially it tells the react router hey whenever you have slash something, this route here
baktnzda, yl boyunca bir eyin getii bir ey olduunu sylemek sadece bir kimlii armak demektir.
is meant, so just call an ID.
Veya esas olarak, reaktr ynlendiricisine heyecanla
And yes this will interfere with this route, I'll take care about this in a second by simply changing
Ve evet, bu rota etkileyecek, nk stten alta ayrtrld iin pozisyonlar
the positions because it's parsed from top to bottom.
deitirerek bir saniye iinde bununla ilgileniyorlar.
So new post is recognized first and this doesn't accidentally catch this because new posts of course
Dolaysyla yeni mesaj ilk nce tannr ve yanllkla yakalamamaktayz nk yeni yaynlar tabii ki kimlik
could be interpreted as an ID, because all we're saying is we have something dynamic here.
olarak yorumlanabilir, nk biz sadece burada dinamik bir eyimiz var demektir.
So that is a route parameter,
Yani bu Rota parametresi.
now of course we also want to make sure that we pass that parameter when clicking on a route
Elbette, bir rotay tklarken bu parametrenin getiinden emin olmak istiyoruz.
now. For that we need to handle a click on a single post in the post component and there would be two
post bileenlerinde tek bir yayn tklatmamz gerekiyor ve bunu yapmann iki yolu var.
ways of doing that.
Bunun iin
The first is to simply wrap that post component we output here with a link
Birincisi, burada ktmz yazlan bileeni bir balantyla sarmaktr.
and that would be perfectly fine,
Ve bu ok iyi olurdu.
it may be the default way you do it.
eytana yaptnz ekilde olabilir.
So let me quickly do this, I'll import link in curly bracers from react-router-dom and I use link and
Bu yzden beni Re-act router Dom'dan Cali bracers'daki tm ithalat balantsn hemen yaparm ve balanty kullanyorum ve
not nav link because I don't plan on styling the active post, though of course you could do that. Now
balanty nav etmiyorum, nk etkin yaz tarzlandrmay planlamyorum elbette tabii ki buradan
here,
yapabilirsiniz.
I'll then wrap this post element here with this link component, just like that and I'll wrap it in parentheses
saracam ve parantez iine koyacam, bylece bunlar birden fazla satra blebileceimden biraz daha kolay okunur hale getiriyorum.
so that I can split these over multiple lines because that makes it a bit easier to read.
Daha sonra bu ana eyi burada bu balant bileeni ile
So now we're essentially returning a link and there we now have to set to to something dynamic and
imdi esas olarak bir balant dndryoruz ve imdi ikisini dinamik bir ey haline getirmeliyiz ve
that dynamic should be our ID.
o dinamik bizim fikrimiz olmaldr.
Potentially of course if you have longer URLs where you have something like post/ and then
Elbette, elinde daha uzun zamandr ya da baka yerlerde posta yazs ve ardndan kimlik numaras gibi bir ey
the ID,
varsa potansiyel olarak.
you might also mix a string and then your ID or whatever it is. Here
Ayrca bir dize ve daha sonra kimlii veya burada ne olursa olsun kartrabilirsiniz.
however, we're just handling slash and then directly the ID,
Bununla birlikte, yalnzca eik izgi ve ardndan dorudan kimlii ele alyoruz.
So there is no string path in front of the ID,
Bu yzden Kimliin nnde sicim paras yok.
I just need to pass the ID itself. So I want to go to post.id here,
Kimliini kendim geirmem gerekiyor, bu yzden burada kimlie ev sahiplii yapmak istiyorum.
that is essentially what I want to do,
Aslnda bunu yapmak istiyorum.
I want to navigate to this URL and you can still add slash in front of it like this.
Buna erimek istiyorum ve yine de bunun gibi eik izgi ekleyebilirsiniz.
So now with that, we're passing the post.id
Bu yzden imdi onunla posta kimlii geiyoruz.
let's now go back to the blog component and make sure we load the post component when going to this
imdi blok bileene geri dnelim ve bu Ynlendirici'ye giderken yaz bileenini yklediimizden
route here.
emin olalm.
So for that and the blog component, I'll add the import of.
Yani bunun iin blok bileeni veya ithalat eklemek.
Post from
Gnderen.
and now that's in the full post component,
Ve imdi bu tam sonras bileeninde.
FullPost
Tam yaz.
.js
J. S. Ve bu nedenle belki de burada tam yaz olarak adlandrlm ve oradan tam yaz ykleyelim.
and therefore maybe it's also name this full post here and then let's load full post down there.
imdi tam post bileenine sahibiz.
Now we have the full post component,
imdi tm dosyalar saklayalm ve uygulamaya geri dnelim.
let's now save all files and go back to the application
Ve o kilit hatay alalm
and get that key error because obviously forgot this. In the post component when looping through all
nk aka bu post bileeninde unuttuysanz, link tm elementler dizisindeki d edir.
these elements, link is now the outer element in our array of elements here
letiler iin kilit zellik tm postaya deil de balantya eklenmemelidir.
for posts, so that key property should now also be added to the link and not to the post,
Her zaman dngnn en dndaki eleman zerinde olmaldr.
it always has to be on the outmost element in your loop.
Bununla birlikte hata mesajndan kurtulduk.
With that however we got rid of the error message
Ve imdi postay tklarsam,
and now if I click on the post, you can actually see that there is the ID in the URL and you see please
L'nizde kimlii olduunu grebilir ve burada artk ok mantkl olmayan postay seersiniz.
select the post here which doesn't make too much sense anymore.
Postalar tam olarak yklemediimiz halde
It makes sense in one way though, we don't load the posts successfully because this.props.id in the full
mantkl geliyor, nk tam posta bileeni iindeki sahne kimlii artk ayarlanmad.
post component is not set anymore,
Baka bir yolda getiimiz parametre bu ekilde alnamad.
it's not how we retrieved the parameter we're passing through the URL.
Bu ie yaramyor.
So this is not working,
Ne alyor olsa.
what is working though
Bunu, bavurularmzda, yaynlar tklayp farkl kimlikler ykleyebildiimizden dorulayabiliriz.
we can confirm this in our application is that we can click on posts and load different IDs.
Bu biz arzalyoruz.
This is working,
Ayrca bileene yklyoruz.
we're also loading the component.
imdi sadece o parametrenin kartlmas zerinde almaya ihtiyacmz var.